<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-ace-extend-dtls-authorize-07" number="9430" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" updates="9202" obsoletes="" tocDepth="2" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" xml:lang="en" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.16.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CoAP-DTLS Extension to TLS">Extension of the Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) Profile for Authentication and Authorization for Constrained Environments (ACE) to Transport Layer Security (TLS)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9430"/>
    <author initials="O." surname="Bergmann" fullname="Olaf Bergmann">
      <organization abbrev="TZI">Universität Bremen TZI</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Bremen</city>
          <code>D-28359</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bergmann@tzi.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J" surname="Preuß Mattsson" fullname="John Preuß Mattsson">
      <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson AB</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Stockholm</city>
          <code>164 80</code>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>john.mattsson@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Selander" fullname="Göran Selander">
      <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson AB</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Stockholm</city>
          <code>164 80</code>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>goran.selander@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2023"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <workgroup>ace</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet of Things (IoT)</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet of Things</keyword>
    <keyword>IOT</keyword>
    <keyword>OAuth</keyword>
    <keyword>Access Token</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document updates "Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) Profile for Authentication and Authorization for Constrained Environments (ACE)" (RFC 9202) by specifying that the profile applies to TLS as well as DTLS.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The Authentication and Authorization for Constrained Environments (ACE) framework <xref target="RFC9200"/> defines an architecture for lightweight authentication between the Client, Resource Server (RS), and Authorization Server (AS), where the Client and RS may be constrained.

      "Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) Profile for Authentication and Authorization for Constrained Environments (ACE)" <xref target="RFC9202"/> only specifies the use of DTLS <xref target="RFC9147"/> for transport layer security between the nodes in the ACE architecture but works equally well for Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8446"/>. For many constrained implementations, the Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP) over UDP <xref target="RFC7252"/> is the first choice, but when deploying ACE in networks controlled by other entities (such as the Internet), UDP might be blocked on the path between the Client and the Resource
Server, and the Client might have to fall back to CoAP over TCP <xref target="RFC8323"/> for NAT or firewall traversal. This dual support for security over TCP as well as UDP is already supported by the Object Security for Constrained RESTful Environments (OSCORE) profile <xref target="RFC9203"/>.</t>
      <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC9202"/> by specifying that the profile applies to TLS as well as DTLS. It only impacts the transport layer security channel between the Client and Resource Server. The same access rights are valid in case transport layer security is provided by either DTLS or TLS. The same access token can be used by either DTLS or TLS between a given (Client, RS) pair. Therefore, the value <tt>coap_dtls</tt> in the <tt>ace_profile</tt> parameter of an Authorization Server to Client (AS-to-Client) response or in the <tt>ace_profile</tt> claim of an access token indicates that either DTLS or TLS can be used for transport layer security.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      <t>Readers are expected to be familiar with the terms and concepts
described in <xref target="RFC9200"/> and <xref target="RFC9202"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="specific-changes-to-rfc-9202">
      <name>Specific Changes to RFC 9202</name>
      <t>The main changes to <xref target="RFC9202"/> specified in this document are limited
to replacing "DTLS" with "DTLS/TLS" throughout the document. This
essentially impacts the use of secure transport, as described in
Sections <xref target="RFC9202" section="3.2.2" sectionFormat="bare"/>, <xref target="RFC9202" section="3.3.2" sectionFormat="bare"/>, <xref target="RFC9202" section="4" sectionFormat="bare"/>, and <xref target="RFC9202" section="5" sectionFormat="bare"/>.</t>
      <t>In addition to this, the Client and Resource Server behavior is
updated to describe the case where either or both DTLS and TLS may be
available, as described in the following section.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="connection-establishment">
      <name>Connection Establishment</name>
      <t>Following the procedures defined in <xref target="RFC9202"/>, a
Client can retrieve an access token from an Authorization Server in
order to establish a security association with a specific Resource
Server. The <tt>ace_profile</tt> parameter in the Client-to-AS request and
AS-to-Client response is used to determine the ACE profile that the
Client uses towards the Resource Server.</t>
      <t>The <tt>ace_profile</tt> parameter indicates the use of the DTLS
profile for ACE, as defined in <xref target="RFC9202"/>. Therefore, the Client typically
first tries using DTLS to connect to the Resource Server. If this fails, the
Client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> try to connect to the Resource Server via TLS.</t>
      <t>As resource-constrained devices are not expected to support both
transport layer security mechanisms, Clients and Resource Servers
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> support DTLS and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> support TLS. A Client that implements either
TLS or DTLS but not both might fail in establishing a secure
communication channel with the Resource Server altogether. Nonconstrained
Clients and Resource Servers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> support both TLS and DTLS.</t>
      <t>Note that a communication setup with an a priori unknown Resource
Server typically employs an initial unauthorized resource request, as
illustrated in <xref target="RFC9202" section="2" sectionFormat="of"/>. If this
message exchange succeeds, the Client <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> first use the same
underlying transport protocol for the establishment of the security
association to the Resource Server (i.e., DTLS for UDP, and TLS for TCP).</t>
      <t>As a consequence, the selection of the transport protocol used for the
initial unauthorized resource request also depends on the transport
layer security mechanism supported by the Client.  Clients that
support either DTLS or TLS but not both <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use the transport
protocol underlying the supported transport layer security mechanism
for an initial unauthorized resource request to the Resource
Server, as in <xref target="RFC9202" section="2" sectionFormat="of"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>In the "ACE Profiles" registry, the Description and Reference fields
   have been updated as follows for coap_dtls:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
	<dt>Name:</dt><dd>coap_dtls</dd>
	<dt>Description:</dt> <dd>Profile for delegating client Authentication and
Authorization for Constrained Environments by establishing a Datagram
Transport Layer Security (DTLS) or Transport Layer Security (TLS)
channel between resource-constrained nodes.</dd>
      <dt>CBOR Value:</dt> <dd>1</dd>
      <dt>Reference:</dt>  <dd><xref target="RFC9202"/>, RFC 9430</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security consideration and requirements in <xref target="RFC9202"/>, TLS 1.3 <xref target="RFC8446"/>, and BCP 195 <xref target="RFC8996"/> <xref target="RFC9325"/> also apply to this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8323.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9147.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9200.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9202.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8996.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9203.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9325.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgments">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Marco Tiloca"/> for reviewing this
specification.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
